International Alliance of Women Records, 1906-2009 (bulk 1913-1973)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
International Alliance of Women records
1906-2009
1913-1973
International Alliance of Women
313
7 boxes (2.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Approximately half of the collection consists of programs and other material related to biennial conferences, in particular the 12th Congress held in Istanbul, 1935. Material from this Congress includes committee reports and resolutions, correspondence, programs, publicity, speeches, and memorabilia. Documentation for other conferences is more sparse, consisting mainly of programs. There are also official conference reports (1906-61) and general documents such as agendas, publicity, position papers, newsletters, and printed material. Major topics addressed include women's rights, women's suffrage, the international women's movement, peace, and the United Nations.
At a 1902 meeting in Washington, D.C., delegates from ten countries, believing that a new international organization devoted to women's suffrage was needed, planned to meet in Berlin to form a permanent organization. Delegates from eight nations founded the International Woman Suffrage Alliance (IWSA) in 1904 as an unconditionally pro-suffrage and explicitly feminist alternative to the International Council of Women, which had failed to take a clear pro-suffrage position. The Alliance established suffrage as its primary goal from the beginning and maintained votes for women as its sole concern until just before World War I. Beginning in 1913 the group began to address wider issues including prostitution, peace, equal pay, women's right to employment, the nationality of married women, and slavery. In 1915, individual members of IWSA from warring countries had met in the Hague and were instrumental in setting up what has become another highly regarded sister organization, the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom.
By the 1920s the Alliance was divided into groups of enfranchised and disenfranchised women and, although it continued to press for woman suffrage in countries without it, the organization also adopted peace and equality as major goals. Changing its name to the International Alliance of Women for Suffrage and Equal Citizenship in the late 1920s, the group, headed by Margery Corbett Ashby, maintained its commitment to peace throughout the inter-war period. Although it became increasingly similar to the International Council of Women after the 1910s it stubbornly maintained its separate structure and identity. Emerging intact out of the chaos of World War II the organization adopted a program of peace, democracy, women's rights, and support for the United Nations. In 1946 the name International Alliance of Women was adopted with the sub-title Equal Rights - Equal Responsibilities.
In its present-day work the IAW "affirms that full and equal enjoyment of human rights is due to all women and girls. The IAW maintains that a prerequisite to securing these rights is the universal ratification and implementation without reservation of the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women (CEDAW). The importance and value of women's contributions as equal partners has been acknowledged in numerous United Nations World Conferences held during the past decades." [Source: IAW Web site http://www.womenalliance.org/history.html]
Approximately half of the collection consists of programs and other material related to biennial conferences, in particular the 12th Congress held in Istanbul, 1935. Material from this Congress includes committee reports and resolutions, correspondence, programs, publicity, speeches, and memorabilia. Documentation for other congresses is more sparse, consisting mainly of programs. There are also official conference reports (1906-61) and general documents such as agendas, publicity, position papers, newsletters, and printed material. Major topics addressed include women's rights, women's suffrage, the international women's movement, peace, and the United Nations.
The International Alliance of Women Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exception: Electronic documents (on CD) and printouts, 1999-2007, are closed per donor instructions.
The International Alliance of Women records were given to the Sophia Smith Collection by Louisa Fast, Smith College Class of 1898.
Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947; International Alliance of Women--History--Sources; International Woman Suffrage Alliance--History; Feminists--History--20th century--Sources; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Turkey--History--20th century--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Women's rights--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--United States-History--Sources
The Sophia Smith Collection has a full run of IAW newsletters in the Periodicals Collection under the titles: International Women's Suffrage News (1906-13); Jus Suffragi (1913-24); and International Women's News (1906-2009). Issues from 1906-14 are also available on microfilm.
A larger collection of International Alliance of Women Records is held by The Women's Library at London Metropolitan University.
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General
  - Correspondence, reports, and constitution 1920-67, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets 1967, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - International Woman Suffrage News and brochure 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photo book of membersundated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Congresses
  - International Woman Suffrage Alliance program, Copenhagen 1906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 4th Conference, Amsterdam: report 1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 5th Conference, London: report 1909, [original and preservation copy - please use photocopy] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 6th Congress, Stockholm: report 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 7th Congress, Budapest: report, press, program, and correspondence 1913, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 8th Congress, Geneva: report and program 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 9th Congress, Rome: report 1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 10th Congress, Paris: report 1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 10th Congress, Paris: Committee on Family Endowment or Allowances Report 1926 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report and Resolutions of the First Peace Study Conference, Amsterdam 1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 11th Congress, Berlin: report 1929 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 12th Congress, Istanbul 1935 (Box 2)
    - Report and proofs of reports (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - League of Women Voters material and committee reports (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Committee reports, resolutions, news clippings, and correspondence, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Correspondence - (Louisa Fast, Press Representative) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Publicity and photographs (Carrie Chapman Catt, Margaret Corbett Ashby, Louisa Fast, and Latife Bekir)undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Speeches (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 13th Congress, Copenhagen: report 1939 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 14th Congress, Interlaken: report 1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 15th Congress, Amsterdam: report and program 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 16th Congress, Naples: publicity and report 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - S. E. Asia Regional Group's Inaugural Regional Conference on "The Education of Women in a Changing East," Colombo: report 1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 17th Congress (Golden Jubilee Congress), Colombo, Ceylon 1955 (Box 3)
    - Pamphlet, program, and report (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Journey Towards Freedom: Written for the Golden Jubilee of the International Alliance of Women" (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 18th Congress, Athens: publicity, program, and report 1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Report of International Committee Conference, Teheran 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 19th Congress, Dublin: report and publicity 1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Report of the Hannah Rydh Memorial Seminar, Sierra Leone 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 21st Congress, England: publicity 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 22nd Congress, Konigstein, West Germany: publicity 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 23rd Congress, New Delhi: publicity and itinerary 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Centenary Celebration: program 2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Electronic documents and printouts 1999-2007 (Box 4-5)
  [CLOSED]
- Newsletters2008-09 (Box 7)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - 7th Congress (Budapest): publicity 1913 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Newspapers
    - La Republique16 April 1935 (Map-case Flat file)
    - La Republique18 April 1935 (Map-case Flat file)
    - La Turquie28 April 1935 (Map-case Flat file)